Guide to the Allen Grover Records of the Committee on War Information
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Allen Grover records of the Committee on War Information
1941-1942
MS 1678
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
Records documenting the service of Allen Grover as Associate Director of the federal Office of Facts and Figures (OFF) in 1941-1942. The records consist of memoranda, minutes, public opinion surveys, and reports created by the OFF, which was established in October 1941 by Franklin Delano Roosevelt (FDR) in order to disseminate information to the American public regarding the war effort. The OFF was subsumed into the newly created Office of War Information on 13 June 1942. The records notably document the U.S. Government's policy during World War II on information dissemination, propaganda, public opinion, and the concerns for the "post-war world order."
Grover, Allen, 1900-1993
General note
The records were previously known as the Allen Grover Papers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robinson Grover, 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Documents in this collection originally classified by the U.S. Government have been declassified per E.O. 12958 (as amended), Project # NW 29376, JS/HR-M, 18 Oct 2007.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by type of material and within folders are arranged in reverse chronological order, as received.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of memoranda, minutes, public opinion surveys, and reports documenting Allen Grover's role as Associate Director in the Office of Facts and Figures (OFF). The OFF was established in October 1941 by Franklin Delano Roosevelt (FDR) in order to disseminate information to the American public regarding the war effort. On 13 June 1942 FDR established the Office of War Information, which subsumed the OFF and included the Committee on War Information Policy, of which Grover was a member.
The records notably document the U.S. Government's policy during World War II on information dissemination, propaganda, public opinion, and the concerns for the "post-war world order." A small amount of subject files contains organizational charts, printed ephemera, and materials on topics including rubber production and press monitoring.
Biographical / Historical
Allen Grover (James Allen Grover) was born in St. Louis, Missouri, on August 4, 1900. He graduated from Yale in 1922. He held positions at United American Steamship Lines, and at the brokerage firms of J. G. White & Company and Pynchon & Company. In 1931, Grover became a contributing editor for business and finance at Time magazine. The following year he transferred to Fortune and eventually rose to assistant managing editor. In 1936, Grover became personal assistant to Henry Luce, the head of Time, Inc., and in 1939 was promoted to vice president. In December 1941 Grover joined the U.S. Government Office of Facts and Figures, which became the Office of War Information in June 1942, with a six-month contract as Associate Director under Archibald MacLeish. He left in early July 1942 and returned to Time. Grover retired in 1962 from Time, and died in New York City on May 3, 1993.
Grover, Allen, 1900-1993; United States. Office of Facts and Figures
- Inventory
  - Agendas, Committee on War Information Policy, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Executive orders, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
    - General, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Reorganization, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - War production, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes
    - Committee on War Information Policy, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Meetings, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - State, Army, Navy meetings, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reports
    - Byrd Committee, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Production, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Surveys, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 18-25)
    - United Nations, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Subjects
    - Davis, Elmer, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Neuberger, Richard, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Organization, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Press monitoring, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Printed ephemera -map of the Russian front, 194- (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Rubber, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)